Hi! I’m Sandra, from HEARa.
Welcome to Day 7
of our 10-day Lipreading Challenge,
designed to help you develop
and practice your lipreading skills!
Hearing loss can have a
profound impact on your life.
It touches every interaction.
It can affect your career,
your relationships,
and your happiness.
Join me to explore tips and tricks
on this YouTube channel
to bring confidence and clarity
to relationships in all areas of your life.
Today is a two for one.
We're going to be learning
about W and Q.
Let's start with the W sound.
To make this sound,
your lips round and then open,
and your jaw drops.
It's actually a two-movement sound.
Try saying a W with me,
as in WON’T.
Round your lips,
open your mouth,
and drop your jaw.
WON’T.
And now that you've learned the W,
you also know the Q!
Because Q is K + W!
What do you already know about the K sound?
It's invisible.
So Q is not visible.
You only see the W.
So add Q = K+ W
to your list of invisible sounds!
Watch me as I say
these two words silently:
QUEST and WEST
They look exactly the same.
Here's another pair of words that look the same:
QUAIL and WHALE.
So, “I think I'll order quail from the menu.”
would look the same as
“I think I'll order a whale from the menu.”
if you were a physician,
confusing QUEAZY and WHEEZY
might make a difference to your diagnosis!
Sometimes the Q sound
is not spelled with a Q.
What word looks like wire,
that has a Q sound,
and it's not spelled with a Q?
Wire looks like choir.
Now let's get some practice
lipreading W sounds in sentences.
For the next 10 sentences,
I'll say the sentence silently,
then out loud,
and silently again.
Pay close attention
to the sentences,
because you're going
to see them again.
There's some memory work
involved in today's challenge.
It's another two for one:
lipreading plus memory skills.
The topic is worms.
Are you ready?
Number 1
and the sentence is:
Have you seen worms on the
sidewalk after the rain?
Notice that I had
a questioning look on my face.
My eyes got a little bit wider,
and my eyebrows raised a little bit.
Watch me again:
Number 2
The sentence was:
Worms are wonderful—they work so hard!
Here it is again:
Number 3
The sentence was:
Does a worm make you squirm?
Here it is again:
Number 4
The sentence was:
You will see worms in wet soil.
Number 5
The sentence was:
Wet soil keeps a worm’s skin moist.
Here it is again:
Number 6
The sentence was:
Worms to breathe through their skin.
Here it is again:
The next sentence has two parts.
Number 7
The first part was:
When it is wet and rainy outside,
Number 8
The sentence was:
worms wiggle onto sidewalks.
So now I'm going to do the whole sentence again:
The sentence was:
Worms can eat up to half of
their body weight per day!
Here it is again:
Number 10
The sentence was:
Worms bring water and air into the ground.
Here it is again:
Okay, now I'm going to randomly pick
five of the sentences that we just worked on.
See if you can figure out which
ones I picked.
It's totally okay to guess.
If you can recognize it, you're lip reading!
The answers are written below.
Refer to them if you're not sure.
Are you ready?
Sentence A:
If you're not sure, you can just rewind slightly.
Sentence B:
Sentence C:
Sentence D:
Here's the last one.
Sentence E:
Probably one of the most popular
W words for people with hearing loss
is not worms, but “WHAT?”
“PARDON?” is considered to
be slightly more polite,
but they're both actually
non-specific requests for clarification.
So when you're asking someone,
“What did you say?”
you can use a specific or
a non-specific request for clarification.
A non-specific request such as
“WHAT?” or “PARDON ME?”
or “WHAT DID YOU SAY?”
is actually not so helpful for the person
that you're speaking with.
It doesn't provide any information
about what part of the message
was not understood or
what they can do to make it easier for you.
So a non-specific request
does not do anything to resolve
the communication issue.
On the other hand, a specific request for clarification
is considered to be more effective,
because it gives the other
person some information.
Some examples are:
“I heard the first
part about worms being hard working, but
I didn't get what you said after that.”
Or, “Did you say that worms eat up to
10 times their body weight per day?”
Another tip is to give the other person
some information about what would help
in terms of the way they are speaking to you.
Most people are more focused on
what they're saying
than how they're saying it.
Such as:
“Could you slow down?”
Notice how I said that slowly—maybe
the chameleon effect will work for me here!
Or, “I can't hear you when the tap is running.
Hang on for a second I'll turn the water off.”
Next time you can't hear
what someone is saying,
try making a specific request
for clarification and let me know
how that goes for you in the comments.
I would also love to hear
how you're doing with the challenge.
I hope you find this helpful.
If you want to learn even more
because there's lots more I can teach you
about lip reading and communication tips,
I encourage you to sign up for my online classes.
The classes are standalone
so you can take them in any order.
And you can just take one,
or if you really want to improve
your communication skills,
sign up for the whole series!
Please Like, Subscribe, and especially,
share with others.
Thank you, thank you thank you!
We'll see you tomorrow for Day 8.
Bye!